AI agents can choose operational tools. But autonomy is not authority.
PALO-AI makes authority, policy, oversight and evidence visible.
Pattern A: a Visual Governance Decision Gate normalizes each proposed action
and exposes Allowed, Approval Required and Denied outcomes.
The current visual gate is useful and testable, but advisory:
a workflow editor can still remove it.
Pattern B: the Governed Executor keeps credentials behind PALO
and accepts only registered executors with schema-valid arguments.
Policy runs outside the model. A one-time capability is consumed
before an allowlisted executor performs the action.
Pattern C: human approval is bound to the digest
of one exact, immutable Action Claim.
The backend revalidates the same claim before secure resume.
Authenticated mobile delivery remains under development.
Pattern D: Workflow Admission assesses workflow JSON, hosts,
destructive operations and missing governance coverage.
Instance-level blocking and versioned workflow admission
are specified future capabilities, not current claims.
The installable alpha runs in n8n 2.30.7 with encrypted credentials
and three visible decision outputs.
It creates Action Claim 1.1, adds n8n execution metadata,
preserves immutable approval resume and fails closed.
In the live test, the authenticated PALO gateway denied
an action whose agent profile was deliberately missing.
n8n routed the decision to Denied with authorized set to false.
A successful denial is meaningful preview evidence.
Developer preview: challenge the contracts with safe workflows.
n8n orchestrates. PALO governs whether it is authorized.